<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://joanne-nguy.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://joanne-nguy.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-03-26T16:54:25+00:00</updated><id>https://joanne-nguy.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">sweet rice wine</title><link href="https://joanne-nguy.github.io/blog/2025/sweet-rice-wine/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="sweet rice wine"/><published>2025-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://joanne-nguy.github.io/blog/2025/sweet-rice-wine</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joanne-nguy.github.io/blog/2025/sweet-rice-wine/"><![CDATA[<h4 id="abstract">Abstract</h4> <p>A recipe from my childhood with fragrant rice and bubbly, sweet juice. This is my take on the Vietnamese way of preparing and having this dessert.</p> <p>Heavily inspired by <a href="http://nasilemaklover.blogspot.com/2015/11/homemade-yellow-glutinous-rice-wine.html">Sonia’s</a> recipe and <a href="https://vietstreetfoods.blogspot.com/2013/10/sweet-fermented-rice-com-ruou.html">Huu’s</a> background.</p> <h4 id="materials">Materials</h4> <ul> <li>Pan with steamer</li> <li>Metal steaming bowl</li> <li>2 Sterilized clear glass jars (A 26+ oz jar and a 3+ oz jar)</li> <li>Sterilized (metal) spoon(s)</li> <li>Mortar and Pestle or Food Processor</li> </ul> <h4 id="reagents">Reagents</h4> <table> <thead> <tr> <th style="text-align: left"> </th> <th style="text-align: left">Ingredient</th> <th style="text-align: left">Amount</th> <th style="text-align: left">Preparation</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"><input type="checkbox"/></td> <td style="text-align: left">Sweet or Black glutinous rice</td> <td style="text-align: left">1 cup</td> <td style="text-align: left">None</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"><input type="checkbox"/></td> <td style="text-align: left">Water</td> <td style="text-align: left">&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;1 and 1/2 cup for steaming&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;More for rinsing&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</td> <td style="text-align: left">Filtered (preferred) or tap</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"><input type="checkbox"/></td> <td style="text-align: left"><a href="https://www.amazon.com/HanHeng-Taste-Shanghai-Yeast-Balls/dp/B01DHHD6BC">Chinese distiller’s yeast balls</a></td> <td style="text-align: left">4 Tbsp (40g)</td> <td style="text-align: left">None</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"><input type="checkbox"/></td> <td style="text-align: left">Optional: Granulated sugar</td> <td style="text-align: left">2 Tbsp</td> <td style="text-align: left">None</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p><br/></p> <h4 id="procedure">Procedure</h4> <p>Glutinous Rice Preparation</p> <ol> <li>Wash and rinse glutinous rice with cold water in the metal steaming bowl.</li> <li>Soak rice with 1/2” of cool (filtered) water for 1 hour.</li> <li>While waiting, prepare the yeast balls by grinding into fine powder. Seal in a dry, sterile jar.</li> <li>Fill the pan with water without allowing any into the steaming basket. Boil water on medium heat.</li> <li>Once the steaming basket is boiling, set heat to medium-low and place soaked rice with water in the steaming basking. Steam for 30-40 mins, mixing rice with a sterile spoon halfway through. <ul> <li>Try not to break any rice grains when mixing.</li> <li>Rice is done cooking when there is no liquid visible and rice appears evenly soft and translucent.</li> </ul> </li> <li>Remove metal bowl with steamed rice from the steamer basket and allow to cool completely at room temperature, approximately 1 hour.</li> <li>Wash hands with soap thoroughly.</li> <li>Using your hands, form flat discs with the glutinous rice. Using a sterile spoon, lightly dust the rice with powdered yeast. Flip the rice disc and dust with more powdered yeast.</li> <li>Add the yeast-covered disc to a sterilized jar.</li> <li>(Optional) For a stronger wine, lightly dust the rice with granulated sugar.</li> <li>Repeat steps 8-9 with the remaining rice.</li> <li>Lightly screw on jar lid to allow gases to escape and place in a warm, dark area.</li> </ol> <p>Fermenting</p> <ol> <li>The distiller’s yeast has an optimal operating temperature of 28<sup>o</sup>C. <ul> <li>I created a warm space by putting a cloth over the jar and a bowl of hot water in the oven and replaced the water twice a day. Any warm, dark space will work.</li> </ul> </li> <li>Let the rice ferment for 48-72 hours depending on ambient temperature and wine flavor preference. <ul> <li>A cloudy liquid will pool in the jar and bubbles will rise to the top. This indicates that the rice is actively fermenting.</li> <li>Sterilize a spoon and taste the wine. Place the jar in the fridge when the flavor is sweet and no longer like yeast.</li> </ul> </li> </ol> <p>Serving</p> <ol> <li>Using a sterilized spoon, scoop the rice and liquid into your serving bowl.</li> <li>The rice wine may be enjoyed as is. For a sweet chewiness, top with cooked mung bean; if it’s too strong, dilute with water or yakult.</li> </ol> <table> <tr> <th>Yield</th> <td>A 26 oz jar of rice wine. Serving size is ~2 oz.</td> </tr> <tr> <th>Storage</th> <td>Store rice wine in the fridge for 1-2 weeks or until smell or flavor changes.</td> </tr> </table> <p><br/></p> <h4 id="discussion">Discussion</h4> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1630056656591-0cba044ba94f?q=80&amp;w=2576&amp;auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;ixid=M3wxMjA3fDB8MHxwaG90by1wYWdlfHx8fGVufDB8fHx8fA%3D%3D" class="img-fluid mx-auto d-block rounded z-depth-1" width="50%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Rice wine dessert. Photo from Unsplash. </div> <p>This dessert comes from warm memories of the fragrance of rice wine. Everytime my mom made a big batch, all of it would be eaten by the end of the week. When I moved, I made many attempts to replicate this dessert, but there were many failures before I figured out the best way to maintain a warm environment suited for distiller yeast activity. I remember the dessert from my childhood was strong and oftentimes bitter - my mom’s recipe used the dangerous addition of sugar, which gave the yeast an additional food source to turn into alcohol. I prefer my recipe without the added sugar, as the dessert ends up much sweeter this way, although with lower alcohol content - not a bad thing depending who you ask.</p> <p>This recipe uses sweet glutinous rice which is short-grain white rice. I’ve yet to attempt this recipe with my childhood preference of black glutinous rice. The resulting dessert is chewy, with the nuttiness of the grain complementing the light rice fragrance. In my memory it was a whole other dish in comparison to the light, sweet and bubbly dessert in this recipe.</p> <p>Sourcing the distiller’s yeast balls may prove difficult. I found some at a local 99 Ranch with the help of a store associate who was just as surprised as me when we found it on the top shelf of the sugar section. In the reagents, I’ve listed a random Amazon store to show what it looks like but feel free to source from elsewhere.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="recipes"/><category term="ferments,"/><category term="sweet"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[a sweet glutinous rice dessert with low alcohol content]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">brown butter chocolate chip cookies</title><link href="https://joanne-nguy.github.io/blog/2025/bb-choco-chips/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="brown butter chocolate chip cookies"/><published>2025-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://joanne-nguy.github.io/blog/2025/bb-choco-chips</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://joanne-nguy.github.io/blog/2025/bb-choco-chips/"><![CDATA[<h4 id="abstract">Abstract</h4> <p>A recipe that I’ve perfected and have baked dozens and dozens of batches - here’s my take on the classic chocolate chip cookie!</p> <p>Heavily inspired by <a href="https://sallysbakingaddiction.com/brown-butter-toffee-chocolate-chip-cookies/">Sally’s</a> recipe.</p> <h4 id="materials">Materials</h4> <ul> <li>(Recommended) Weighing scale</li> <li>Silicone spatula</li> <li>Light-colored pan</li> <li>2 Mixing bowls (preferably heat-proof)</li> <li>Large sifter</li> <li>Measuring cups/spoons</li> <li>Cookie scoop (2 Tbsp or other)</li> <li>Freezer bag</li> <li>2 Large baking sheets</li> <li>Cooling rack</li> <li>Silicone cookie sheet</li> <li>(Optional) Mixer with paddle attachment</li> </ul> <h4 id="reagents">Reagents</h4> <table> <thead> <tr> <th style="text-align: left"> </th> <th style="text-align: left">Ingredient</th> <th style="text-align: left">Amount</th> <th style="text-align: left">Preparation</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"><input type="checkbox"/></td> <td style="text-align: left">Unsalted Butter</td> <td style="text-align: left">1 cup (16 Tbsp; 226g)</td> <td style="text-align: left">Room temperature</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"><input type="checkbox"/></td> <td style="text-align: left">Packed light or dark brown sugar</td> <td style="text-align: left">1 cup (200g)</td> <td style="text-align: left">None</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"><input type="checkbox"/></td> <td style="text-align: left">Granulated sugar</td> <td style="text-align: left">1/2 cup (100g)</td> <td style="text-align: left">None</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"><input type="checkbox"/></td> <td style="text-align: left">Optional: (Malted) milk powder</td> <td style="text-align: left">2 Tbsp</td> <td style="text-align: left">None</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"><input type="checkbox"/></td> <td style="text-align: left">Large eggs</td> <td style="text-align: left">2</td> <td style="text-align: left">Room temperature</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"><input type="checkbox"/></td> <td style="text-align: left">Pure vanilla extract</td> <td style="text-align: left">2 Tsp</td> <td style="text-align: left">None</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"><input type="checkbox"/></td> <td style="text-align: left">All-purpose flour</td> <td style="text-align: left">2 and 1/2 cups (313g)</td> <td style="text-align: left">Spooned &amp; leveled</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"><input type="checkbox"/></td> <td style="text-align: left">Baking soda</td> <td style="text-align: left">1 Tsp</td> <td style="text-align: left">None</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"><input type="checkbox"/></td> <td style="text-align: left">Salt (non-iodized)</td> <td style="text-align: left">1/2 Tsp</td> <td style="text-align: left">None</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"><input type="checkbox"/></td> <td style="text-align: left">Extra-dark chocolate chips</td> <td style="text-align: left">1/2 cup (50g)</td> <td style="text-align: left">None</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"><input type="checkbox"/></td> <td style="text-align: left">Optional: Heath Bar Bits O’ Brickle English Toffee</td> <td style="text-align: left">1/2 cup (75g)</td> <td style="text-align: left">None</td> </tr> <tr> <td style="text-align: left"><input type="checkbox"/></td> <td style="text-align: left">Optional: Flaky sea salt</td> <td style="text-align: left">1/2 Tsp</td> <td style="text-align: left">None</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p><br/></p> <h4 id="procedure">Procedure</h4> <p>Prepare Wet Ingredients</p> <ol> <li>In a heat-proof bowl, add brown sugar and granulated sugar.</li> <li>(Optional) Place the heat-proof bowl in an ice bath.</li> <li>Brown the butter: <ol> <li>Heat a light-colored pan to medium heat on the stove.</li> <li>Cut softened butter into small, equally-sized slices.</li> <li>Once pan has heated up, add butter.</li> <li>Continuously stir with silicone spatula until cubes have melted.</li> <li>Listen for when the crackling subsides and foam starts to clear - milk solids (brown bits) will start forming on the bottom of the pan.</li> <li>Lower heat.</li> <li>Add milk powder and toast for 10s-20s until golden. Continuously stir with silicone spatula.</li> </ol> </li> <li>Immediately take off heat and pour browned butter including milk solids into the heat-proof bowl with sugar.</li> <li>Chill the bowl in ice bath or fridge for 15-20mins until solid but still soft to touch.</li> </ol> <p>Prepare Dry Ingredients</p> <ol> <li>While waiting, sift flour, baking soda and salt into a mixing bowl. Set aside.</li> </ol> <p>Combine Ingredients</p> <ol> <li>Whisk brown butter and sugar on medium until combined ~1 min.</li> <li>Add vanilla and eggs.</li> <li>Whisk wet ingredients on high until fluffy ~2 mins.</li> <li>Whisk on low. Add half of dry ingredients until combined. Add the rest of the dry ingredients until combined. Scrape down the sides of the bowl.</li> <li>Add chocolate chips and toffee bits, if using. Mix with spatula until combined, ensuring bottom is well-mixed.</li> </ol> <p>Chill Dough</p> <ol> <li>Cover mixing bowl and place in the fridge for 1-2 hours.</li> <li>Scoop cookies and place into a freezer bag. Let the dough rest for 24-48 hours.</li> </ol> <p>Bake</p> <ol> <li>Pre-heat the oven and bake at 350<sup>o</sup> for 12-14 mins until bottom edges are golden brown. <ul> <li>Space cookies with 2” between each to allow room for spreading.</li> <li>Time will depend on factors such as cookie scoop size and texture preference. Try 13 mins first, then adjust from there.</li> </ul> </li> <li>Allow cookies to cool on the baking sheet for 10-15 mins before moving to wire rack. Add flaky sea salt.</li> </ol> <table> <tr> <th>Yield</th> <td>20-24 using a 2-Tbsp cookie scoop</td> </tr> <tr> <th>Storage</th> <td>Cookies stay fresh for 3 days on the counter or 1 week in the fridge. Microwave for ~7s before enjoying.<br/>Extra dough can be stored in the freezer for up to 6 months. When baking from frozen, pre-heat the oven to 350<sup>o</sup> and add a minute to the bake time.</td> </tr> </table> <p><br/></p> <h4 id="discussion">Discussion</h4> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1499636136210-6f4ee915583e?q=80&amp;w=2564&amp;auto=format&amp;fit=crop&amp;ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;ixid=M3wxMjA3fDB8MHxwaG90by1wYWdlfHx8fGVufDB8fHx8fA%3D%3D" class="img-fluid mx-auto d-block rounded z-depth-1" width="50%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Brown butter chocolate chip cookies with flaky sea salt on top. Photo from Unsplash. </div> <p>With so many cookie flavors and combinations out there, I find myself coming back to this classic recipe time and time again. If I happen to make too many, it’s a crowd pleaser at gatherings and the platter is empty in no time. The best part about this recipe is that it serves as a great foundation for ingredient substitutions!</p> <h5 id="chocolate-chips">Chocolate Chips</h5> <p>In this recipe, I prefer extra-dark chocolate chips from <a href="https://www.guittard.com/our-chocolate/detail/extra-dark-chocolate-chips">Guittard</a>, but a great substitute are their <a href="https://www.guittard.com/our-chocolate/detail/bake_bittersweet-chocolate-wafers">baking wafers</a> which allows for pools of chocolate throughout the cookie. Chopping them with a steak knife adds smaller shards of chocolate which polka dot the dough and really allows flavours to develop when chilling the dough in the fridge. The bitterness of the dark chocolate really balances the sweetness of the dough and toffee bits!</p> <p>Feel free to add more or less chocolate chips based on your preference. The current recipe aims for about 5 chocolate chips per cookie. Of course, the shape and number of chips will affect cookie spread!</p> <h5 id="brown-butter">Brown Butter</h5> <p>Liquid gold in edible form! In this recipe we add more milk powder to the hot butter to yield even more maillard reactions and nutty goodness. It’s possible to make brown butter in advance, but the milk solids will sink, so be mindful of that when portioning!</p> <p>I’ve also been experimenting with adding other ingredients to the brown butter to enhance flavour. In an attempt to make peaty whiskey taste a little more palatable, I <a href="https://distilleryway.com/articles/brown-butter-fat-washed-whisky-i-tried-it-and-its-incredible">fat-washed</a> it with brown butter (recipe coming soon!). In short, whiskey and liquid brown butter were mixed together and left to sit on the counter to allow the water-soluble and fat-soluble parts of the butter mix with the whiskey. This allows certain flavours to be imparted to the butter, while achieving a smoother whiskey. Whiskey brown butter is a byproduct of this process and perfect for adding to cookies! Be mindful that not all the liquid will be filtered from the butter - my first batch of cookies using the whiskey brown butter ended up being way too gooey. For future batches without whiskey brown butter on hand, a shot of whiskey can be added straight to the wet ingredients in its stead.</p> <h5 id="toffee-bits">Toffee Bits</h5> <p>The most flexible ingredient slot in this recipe! The toffee bits add a bit of caramelly crunch to the otherwise soft texture of the cookies and really complements the flavour profile I’m going for. That said, the toffee bits can be substituted for anything you want - nuts, marshmellows, dried fruit, the possibilities are endless. However, it’s important to understand how extra moisture will affect the spreading of the cookie dough.</p> <h5 id="flour">Flour</h5> <p>Although a staple in the recipe, some or all of the all-purpose flour can be substituted with other types of flour such as rye (for nuttier flavor), bread (for denser, chewier texture) or cake (for airy, light texture). I haven’t experimented with other flours since I still have a Costco-sized bag to go through, but my goal is to try substitutions with rye and bread flours.</p> <p>Other powdered flavour enhancers can be substituted in near equal parts with the flour removed. For example, for an espresso cookie, I substituted 20g of flour for 20g of freshly ground espresso powder, which resulted in a cookie with similar texture and a whole new flavor profile. Other powders to try are malted milk powder (the malt is key since it’s not water soluble and will not affect the wet:dry ratio of the dough), cocoa powder, matcha powder and dehydrated fruit powders.</p> <p>An <a href="https://www.kingarthurbaking.com/blog/2023/12/27/recipe-of-the-year-chocolate-chip-cookies">Arthur chocolate chip recipe</a> calls for the addition of a milk bread roux, Tangzhong. The roux is a combination of (whole) milk and flour cooked on the stove to create a pre-hydrated dough that lends itself to the chewiest texture I’ve ever experienced in a cookie. This is yet another time consuming process adding to an already long protocol, but definitely worth it if you have the time to spare!</p> <h5 id="chilling-time">Chilling Time</h5> <p><a href="https://www.kingarthurbaking.com/blog/2015/05/17/chilling-cookie-dough">Chilling</a> the cookie dough has multiple effects on the final cookie. The most obvious is spread - cold fats, and thus, cold dough will spread less in the oven, lending itself to a smaller and thicker cookie. This helps keep the center moist and gooey while the outside crisps up as it bakes. Conversely, if a thinner, crispy cookie is your aim, then baking cookies without chilling will help you achieve that.</p> <p>When leaving your cookie dough in the fridge for long periods of time, chemical reactions occur in the dough which help develop and deepen the flavors. The enzyme, amylase, that naturally occurs in the flour <a href="https://www.theperfectloaf.com/guides/how-to-autolyse/#h-how-to-autolyse">break down</a> complex carbohydrates into simple sugars. The result is a sweeter, more complex tasting cookie dough. That’s why I recommend chilling cookie dough for 24-48 hours for maximum impact. However, one can’t help but bake a cookie after a short 1 hour chill to taste test.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="recipes"/><category term="cookies,"/><category term="baking,"/><category term="sweet"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[my popular brown butter chocolate chip cookies]]></summary></entry></feed>